thank you
[Music]
hello good evening good day everybody
Welcome to episode 89 of ask Abhijit
today we are discussing Ukraine this is
the Ukraine special as we know uh the
Russian invasion of Ukraine has begun
about 24 to about 48 hours ago or so and
it's still a work in progress so that's
what we are discussing today so before
we go into that I would like to show you
an interesting development that's
happened in the United Nations watch
this and I may say to some
it is exactly
the safety of your Nationals right now
in Ukraine
that you should be the first to vote
to stop the war to save your Nationals
in Ukraine
and not to
think about whether you should or should
not vote because of the safety of your
Nationals
so this is the Ukrainian Ambassador in
the United Nations who is speaking to
the Indian ambassador
and he is saying you should worry about
the safety of your Nationals you know
what this Behavior reminds me of
it reminds me of a gangster this is
Gangster Behavior
it's a gangster you know you know it's
it's the way a diplomat would speak he's
speaking diplomatically his words have
multiple meanings you can interpret in
any way you want but he is essentially
talking like a gangster
he's saying that you know
it would be a shame if something were to
happen to your kids we have your kids it
would be terrible it would be a shame if
something were to happen to them
that is what the Ukrainian Ambassador
was saying to the Indian ambassador he's
issuing a public threat in a in
diplomatic language that's what we are
witnessing right now
right so for those of you who are saying
we should support Ukraine we stand with
Ukraine and all this is the situation
this is pure gangsterism it is as close
a diplomat can ever come to issuing a
public threat in on a public platform so
that is where we stand today Ukraine and
you know what's happened there are there
were about 20 000 Indian students in
Ukraine because our education system is
garbage so our kids have to go to other
countries so about 20 000 Indian uh
students were there
most of them may still be there and
they wanted to come back to India but
the Ukrainian authorities said that if
you leave then you will be suspended and
you will not be allowed to come back so
they were made to stay there
and now
they are facing this problem
and I can assure you that the Russian
troops will never
touch in Indian citizen the Russian
troops will never harm an Indian Citizen
and they are being very careful in the
way they are proceeding there are no
civilian casualties that we that we know
of if there was any civilian casualty it
would be all over the Western media
so they are being very careful they are
not hurting civilians of any nationality
they are being precise and surgical in
their military advance so there is no
question of any civilians being hurt
and yet the Ukrainian Ambassador is
threatening India in this manner worry
about the safety of your citizens
this is the kind of gangsterism you're
seeing in the western media will not
report this
so that's where we are today so uh as
I mean all of you have asked lots of
questions so let us with that said let's
go into the questions and let's let's
talk about the Ukraine situation
so what's the first question
the first question is before the USSR
what's the history of Russia Ukraine and
other countries which are part of the
USSR uh gave us some knowledge about the
relationship of Russia and Ukraine in
the last 100 200 years what's the point
of History what was the point in history
that ruined the relationship okay good
question so listen to understand the
roots of the problem
uh we have to go beyond the last 50 or
100 years or whatever we need to go back
much further in time
so let me give you a brief account of
the history of this region for that
let's go to the map
finally I can show the map again here we
are map so this is India I'm sure you
are all familiar with this part of the
world now let's go westwards do you know
where Ukraine is
well here is Ukraine
this is Russia if you can see my mouse
pointer this is Russia and this is
Ukraine here
so what's the history of this place and
why why did this conflict occur so
that's what we want to understand
so let's go back
in his in time in in time let's go back
about 2000 years so the first so the
ukrainians Russians all these people
other Slavic peoples
there they belong to the Slavic
ethnicity
so the first reference in history
recorded reference in history of the
Slavic people is in the first or second
Century A.D it's the Romans who had
recorded some Slavic ethnic group or
tribe or something in Eastern Europe so
they have always lived in Eastern Europe
the Slavic peoples right
and about so so presently Russia
presently Ukraine Belarus Etc has been
traditionally the homeland of the Slavic
peoples the Russians are the largest
ethnic group among the Slavs the
ukrainians are also slav the serbians
ETC they're all Slavs Belarus and so on
so forth so about a thousand years
before today in the 9th century or so
um
the Vikings they made their way into the
Slavic World there was this uh there was
this leader called I think his name was
rurik who came and who he took over the
leadership of this place of the Slavic
people so the Slavs were a polytheistic
people uh their Chief God was perun or
what we call parjanya in Sanskrit it was
a rain God Thunder God you could you
could see him like Indra for instance
the Vikings also had was the
Scandinavians also had very similar uh
culture so they were able to intermingle
nicely so these guys under
this guy called rurik they became the
leaders of the Slavs for some time even
though they were Vikings so the Slavs
had Viking leadership and these workings
they called themselves ruse
so it is this Viking term ruse that
eventually got attached to the Slavic
peoples and they started called they
calling themselves the kievan ruse their
leader was rudik and then it was Prince
Oleg and so on and so forth
their Capital was Kiev
okay so Kev was the capital of the Kevan
ruse they were the ruse not the
ukrainians
so that is the first capital they had
the Slavic people in their first in the
9th and 10th century and in the 11th
century they became christianized
eventually and so on
and this region called which is now
called Ukraine was eventually called
novorocia novor Rosia means Southern
or rather new Russia so it was mostly
uninhabited for for the longest time and
then eventually you had various kinds of
peoples who made their way into this
place right for instance these kitchen
people
uh the islands uh the bulgars the
Mongols the tatars and eventually the
Russians also made their way in this
place into this place in two Novo Rosia
in the 14th century this place was
called little Russia in the 17th and
18th century the Russians the serbs the
Greeks Etc they moved into this place
and that's when this place got the got
the name novorocia later it was called
ukraina okrana which means the
Borderlands of Russia
so as you can see it's always been
Russian territory now how did the nation
of Ukraine come into being the modern
nation state of Ukraine coming to being
so that for that you have to go back
about 100 years so after the 1917
Revolution in Russia when the Communists
the Bolsheviks came to power
the region that they controlled the USSR
was created and it was divided into
various administrative uh zones
or Soviet Socialist republics SSRS and
one of these republics for
administrative purposes was called
Ukraine
so it is this region that we see here
right
so that that region was created for
administrative purposes
and some territories were added to it
which are all Russian speaking and all
and so on and in 1954 I believe it was
Nikita Khrushchev after the Great War
after the second world war he added the
region called Crimea this this peninsula
over here he added this region for
administrative purposes to Ukraine now
the uh
the constitution of the USSR was such
that all these various republics had the
right to secede from the union but under
under people like Stalin and Khrushchev
Etc the control was so strong that
nobody would even dare to think of
seceding from Russia from the USSR right
now uh so so all these regions were made
part of Ukraine for administrative
purposes the Eastern parts of Ukraine
the luhansk Donetsk
regions which is known as the donbass
region is Russian speaking and strangely
the ukrainians
okay I'll come to that later so what
happened is that after the dissolution
of the USSR in 1989
Ukraine and various other republics
declared their independence because
Russia had very poor leadership very
weak leadership
at the time
so uh
in the 1970s and 1980s the economy of
the USSR was not doing well because
their leadership was not strong enough
and in the 1980s it was Mikhail
gorbachevo came to power he is you could
say the weakest of all the leaders in
the USSR he's the one the West loves the
most and the Russians hate the most
because he presided over the destruction
of the of this country the USSR
so Ukraine became independent in 89 or
91 look it up which year it was I don't
remember all the exact dates Ukraine and
various other republics and so on so
forth they all became independent
Moldova Belarus Lithuania Latvia and so
on they all became independent they all
declared their independence and the
Russian leadership was not strong enough
to keep them together so they were
allowed to become independent and in the
case of Ukraine there were lots of these
uh
Soviet nuclear missiles and Warheads on
Ukrainian territory so what the deal
that was cut for the Ukraine was that
you give up all the Soviet
nuclear weapons in exchange for that we
will cancel all the debt that you may
have to repay because at that time the
USSR owed a lot of debt to various
countries so the Russian Republic said
that we will take care of all the debt
you don't have to pay it Ukraine just
give us back all the nuclear weapons so
that was the deal and the the ukrainians
gave away the nuclear weapons to the to
the Russians and the Russians ensured
that the ukrainians they would not have
to pay any re repay any of the debt and
they also subsidized the development of
Ukraine in the last 20 years more than a
hundred billion or 150 billion dollars
worth of subsidy has been given by
Russia to Ukraine
so uh you had people uh like uh Victor
young
yanukovic who was the president of
Ukraine listen I know there are very
smart people who are watching and who
will watch in the future who will say
you did not mention so and so leader you
did not mention so so and so president I
am giving a very brief condensed
overview of History this is not a
history lesson this is about geopolitics
I'm not going to mention every
irrelevant politician who ever came to
power in Ukraine so in uh November 19
2013 uh Victor yanukovic was the
president of Ukraine
then there was this revolution in
Ukraine the 2014 maidan Revolution the
Euro Medan Revolution so in February I
think 2014 the elected president of
Ukraine with was
ousted
he was thrown out and somebody else was
put in place I think
all right
so this was essentially a pro-eu pro
NATO Pro U.S government that was
installed
in in the place of the legally elected
government of Ukraine okay these are
facts I am not putting any kind of spin
on this these are just hard facts
so a pro NATO regime was installed this
is essentially nothing but a coup that
the West engineered in Ukraine
currently currently as of today I am not
mentioning all the politicians who came
to power if you want a list of
politicians you want to draw History
listen look it up yourself currently the
president is zelinski
right he's a former actor former
comedian whatever right
so so he is in power right now so let's
go back to 2014 again once this coup
happened
so now I can tell you this that
strangely enough the ukrainians in the
past 20 years have not conducted any
census because if they were to conduct a
census what you will find is that there
is a very significant
russian-speaking population across
Ukraine mostly concentrated in the east
and south but in other parts of Ukraine
also right so the Ukrainian language is
a Slavic language
you could call it in some sense a
dialect of Russian in some sense I know
lots of people will say no you are wrong
you're poor Russian blah blah blah you
can leave if you if you think that way
so Ukrainian is a very it's very similar
to Russian the so so essentially it's
the same people it's not a separate
ethnicity separate race separate culture
it's the same culture same people
everything is the same they're ancestors
were the same that sort of thing
so the ukrainians are not willing to
show how many russian-speaking people
live there uh so in 2014 the after this
illegal coup that was engineered by the
West a pro-russian unrest started in
Ukraine uh starting from I think
February 2014.
in March 2014 Mr Putin a next Crimea you
see this this this uh Peninsula over
here that is Crimea it's always been
Russian it was added to Ukraine for
administrative purposes by Nikita
Khrushchev and then after in Ukraine's
Independence it became part of Ukraine
which was Russian territory so Mr Putin
annexed this in um March I think 2014
and then you had the war in donbass in
the luhanskin donuts regions and so on
in May 2014 there was a referendum
okay in in this region
uh so this referendum uh I think what
happened is in April 2014 two
independent republics were announced in
the donuts region the lohansk People's
Republic and the Donetsk people's
republics the Republic in May 2014
referendums were held the donbass status
referendums which sought to legitimize
the establishment of these republics and
the war continued the unrest continued
in 2014 there was this terrible tragedy
this horrific tragedy Malaysia Airlines
flight 17 was shot down they thought it
was a civilian aircraft or whatever a
military aircraft or whatever it was a
horrific disaster
then in September you though you're the
first mints agreement which was a 10 12
point peace plan that was agreed upon uh
and uh so that was in September 2014 the
first Minsk agreement in November 2014
there were general elections in the
donbass region which elected the chief
Executives of the these two republics in
the parliaments of these two republics
by January 2015 the Minsk protocol had
collapsed
so in February 2015
the second means agreement Minsk 2 was
agreed upon which was I think a 13 Point
agreement in which there are a couple of
terms I think Point 12 or 13 or two
three of these that the that both the
sides interpret very differently so
again the Minsk to agreement protocol
has never been adhered to properly and
this fighting continues the separatist
uh sentiment continues among the
russian-speaking people in 2021 there
was a significant escalation of fighting
by the end of 2021 there was a
significant Russian build up in the
regions that uh are adjacent to the
donbass region of Ukraine and whether
various other places and also
interestingly in 2014 I think it is in
December
Belarus changed its Constitution
and which effectively ended the neutral
status of Belarus Belarus is this little
country here it's also a Slavic country
it's it was also part of the USSR so
Belarus amended the Constitution which
essentially makes it nothing but a
satellite state at Best of the of the
Russians
so you can say that Belarus is now
willing to host Russian nuclear weapons
and Russian nuclear missiles and it
could be the Russians who control it so
essentially Belarus is you can say now
annexed by Russia
so Belarus can be considered Russian
territory from now on
so in 2021 there was this Russian build
up end of 21 around Ukraine
significant escalation of fighting
2022 it continued the escalation
continued further and the last 48 hours
we know what happened
Mr Putin has ordered an invasion of
Ukraine now we don't know how far the
invasion will go whether it will be uh
whether Mr Putin will be content to
liberate the donbass region the Eastern
regions of Ukraine the russian-speaking
Russian majority regions of Ukraine or
does he want a complete regime change in
the removal of Mr uh volodimir
um does he does he want to remove the
current uh president of Ukraine so that
is what we need to see that is what we
are going to see in the coming days Mr
whether Mr volodimir zielinski will
remain in power I mean
not in power but in his in his office or
whether he will be removed in some other
uh person will be put in place so if
that happens it is a complete regime
change otherwise if the Russian
incursions uh are stopped at a certain
point then it is a liberation of certain
territories and it's also interesting to
note that some of the Russian uh
incursions into Ukraine Invasion
essentially have happened from the North
Via Belarus
that's interesting so essentially
Belarus is now part of Russia and we are
also seeing now that the Chechen troops
of the of the Russians
are now being readied they have been
prepared to come and occupy parts of
Ukraine the Chechen troops
are the ones so who are in the Caucasus
this region right this is chechnya there
was a horrific Civil War there it was
eventually controlled by Mr Putin it has
come under control the original
specified it is stabilized now in the
church and troops of of the Russian army
are the most battle-hardened troops they
know how to deal with everything
including insurgencies including street
fighting including guerrilla warfare
they can deal with everything they are
the ones who will be
put into place
during in into Ukraine so they will be
able to deal with any Insurgency that
may happen in Ukraine because obviously
the West is not happy with what's
happening the Americans are not happy
the NATO is not happening Happy with
what's happening uh
and they may try to ferment Insurgency
and all after the Russian takeover of
the of the place so that is where we are
and that is what I can tell you about
the history
of this place
right
foreign
okay two more questions what is the
primary motive of Putin for The Invasion
apart from the two territories Lohan's
Donuts Russia is a military power
superpower but a weak economy so why
should they go for war is it if it is
because China and economic superpower
supports them
because of this if Russia becomes an
ally of China what should India do as
India's most trustable alliances rather
than the US will this change Russia
Pakistan relationship in affect India
okay let's let's go into the motif let's
let's not take all the questions let's
go into the motives what is the primary
motive of Mr Putin for his invasion see
the first thing is this illegal regime
change this completely undemocratic
regime change that was that was affected
by the West
in 2014 when the elected president the
elected government was ousted right uh
Victor yanukovich the government in
Pietro poroshenko was installed in his
place that is completely illegal and
Democratic the West talks about a
rules-based or Global Order and
democracy democracy and liberalism
where did all that go when they did this
regime change
so and then after this regime change
happened the new regime in Ukraine which
is a pro-west pro-us regime was making
moves to become a part of NATO
NATO is what is NATO NATO during the
Cold War was the uh American
anti-russian Alliance so NATO is the
North Atlantic Treaty Organization the
U.S is part of it I believe I'm not sure
if Canada is part of it look it up look
it up okay I'm not going to give you I
don't remember everything
but uh France is part of it Germany is
part of it the UK is part of it in
various other countries in Western
Europe are part of NATO it was an
anti-ussr alliance after the dissolution
of the USSR
NATO for some time we don't have any
real meaning it is essentially the the
way of the U.S to control Europe
right because you have U.S troops
permanently stationed in Germany which
essentially tells you that Germany is
under U.S occupation it's under American
occupation there's no other nice way of
putting it
imagine if you had American troops
permanently stationed in in India what
would that mean it means India is under
U.S occupation nothing else
so Germany is currently under the U.S
occupation
and so on and so forth right so and
there was this uh deal that was agreed
upon
after 1991 I believe that NATO will not
expand further east
that countries Nations that used to be
under the uh part of the uh
part of the Soviet Bloc would not be
incorporated into NATO that was the
agreement that was made between Russia
and NATO and now they are trying to
break the agreement because they were
trying to bring Ukraine into NATO ukrie
the they changed the regime illegally in
undemocratically and then the new regime
was making moves to join NATO that is a
red line Mr Putin will never allow
anyone to cross that is simply
unacceptable because that is the
encirclement of Russia if you if you
look at the map
if you look at the map I don't have a
map of all the U.S military bases but it
essentially encircles Russia
imagine if you had Russian military
bases in Canada in Mexico in Cuba all
across the U.S would the U.S not see
this as a declaration of war
in a in a grave threat to their National
Security obviously they would see it
that way but if the Russian seat is a
threat to National Security it should
they should tolerate it that's the kind
of uh attitude the US has so obviously
Mr Putin is not going to uh accept that
and when the Ukrainian started making
moves for joining NATO that was the red
line that that Mr Putin could not allow
them to cross because then everything is
up for grabs
so that's why there is the primary
reason
that's the primary reason why uh Mr
Putin has decided to invade Ukraine
uh and uh so that's what it is and also
because uh because of
you know the media will not highlight
this but the Russians have been claiming
that the ukrainians are committing all
perpetrating all kinds of atrocities
against russian-speaking people
there have been massacres and murders
and disappearances and whatnot okay the
Western media will not corroborate this
so we don't know what to believe what
not to believe we in India believe the
English-speaking media especially if
they speak with a posh British accent or
an American accent and they will never
report all these things but I believe it
may be true why should we only believe
one side of the story the Russians have
been making the claim and actually you
know it it was briefly reported some of
these things were briefly reported
before before they were all swept under
the carpet they were even reported by
the Western media
so these are the reasons why
Mr Putin has gone ahead with the
invasion
harshit says will this war between
Russia and Ukraine be considered to be
an invasion or a first step towards
building the USSR because I think this
whole NATO thing was really not that big
just a stick with which to Russia to
poke Russia and result into a warm
uh okay so so does Mr Putin seek to seek
to rebuild the USSR
I do not agree with the with the with
the perception that Mr Putin is trying
to rebuild the USSR
the USSR was a communist structure it
was a communist nation state there was
communism there was the collectivization
and so on so forth Mr Putin doesn't want
to reintroduce communism into Russia
what he is trying to rebuild is what we
would in India called akhand Russia
which is very different from the USSR
because Russia has its own distinctive
culture it has Orthodox Christianity
which is very different from Western
Christianity right it's very very
different it's very traditional Russian
values are very different Russia is not
part of the West Russia is not a western
Nation it's more of an Eastern nation
it's more of at a Crossroads between
east and west
so what Mr Putin is maybe uh seeking to
do is is uh expand Russia's fear of
influence bring more territories into
his under his control territories which
were historically part of the Russian
Empire or part of the USSR
but he's not recreating the USSR he's
creating a stronger greater Russia
akhand Russia what you could say so that
essentially is what he's doing and he's
trying to keep NATO and the The
Americans
away from what he believes what Russia
has traditionally seen as its sole
sphere of influence where nobody else is
allowed to encroach so that is what he
is doing can it be considered invasion
of course it's an invasion you know
what's funny when the Russians invade
the country when the Russian army moves
into a country it's called an invasion
when
the US Army moves into countries into a
country
whether it's Iraq whether it's anywhere
else it's called Liberation it's not an
invasion it's Liberation we are bombing
democracy into you that's what we are
doing and when the
and when the British Army moves
somewhere it's called civilization we
are civilizing you all so when the West
does it it is either Liberation or
civilization when Russia does it it's an
invasion This Is How They portray
everything
when you have a Russian billionaire he
or she is called an oligarch
when you have an American billionaire
he's called a billionaire a business
magnate a tycoon but not an oligarch
what is this
so that's
how everything is spun around
okay again harshit harshit is on a roll
what was the reason behind Russia to
start their Invasion from South Eastern
part of Ukraine instead of using Belarus
to enter Ukraine which would be closer
way to capture the capital Care which
leads to the fall of the whole nation
are they using similar tactics to what
Vishnu Gupta chanakya said
made a mistake directly targeting the
capital instead of going in a slower way
in game and capture the capital okay
let's look at the map it's a good
question
so why did this is a this is a tactical
question why did they adopt the tactics
of bigger Inversion from the East
because in the east in the in the
donbass region you already have
pro-russia people the majority of the
population is Russian speaking they are
ethnic Russians
even ukrainians are ethnics love the
very close Russians but let's let's call
this people who live in the donbas
ethnic Russians so they were already
essentially under Russian control right
this region it was already declared a
separate
right
so so first of all if you invade from
this region from the east from the
eastern part then you will not face any
resistance so you have less territory to
cover it is already friendly territory
it's already Russian controlled
territory so you start the Invasion from
there you want to take the easiest way
into a country right but then there was
a second move made from Belarus as well
because Belarus again now is Russian
control territory so there are multiple
movements happening I think even from
kharki when all this region
and other places even even from here
they are moving towards the Kiev it
looks like I think there's fighting
happening right now inside gear but on
the outskirts of Kiev so if the invasion
began or appeared to begin from the
eastern part from the Eastern region
because that's where you have Russian
control already established so that's
how it looked but there was also a
signals a simultaneous movement that
happened from Belarus
and that's what's happening right now so
it is it is a multi-pronged movement
that we are seeing
okay what are the different ways in
which a country could be brought down or
surrendered like capture like catching
the Prime Minister President in this
case or taking of capital
and other questions let's take the first
question what are the different ways in
which a country could be brought down or
made to surrender
so this is this is again a tactical
question how do you establish control
your how do you establish your Supremacy
your Dominion your power over a country
first of all you have to control all the
highways
you have to control all the highways you
have to control the ports you have to
control the entry and exit points from
the country highways uh train routes if
any ports and Ukraine has ports secondly
you have to control all the airports so
again you're controlling the entry and
exit of people and other things Goods
material into the country then you need
to cut off the internet take over all
the TV stations all the internet
stations all the radio broadcasting
sessions all of that needs to be shut
down so no propaganda or no
anti-invasion uh messageary messaging
can be uh broadcast
and then eventually you take over all
the main cities and all the local
legislators and all that
and you capture all the all the
important individuals
who traditionally have been in power
so that's what you do that is how you uh
take control of a country so right now
what I am seeing is the Russians are not
going into the cities they are trying to
take control of the highways and all
these they are taking control of the
airports there is fighting around
airports and so on so that's what
they're doing it is always going to be a
systematic thing
and that's how you take over a country
right now I don't think they have made
any move to capture the this guy
uhlinski or anybody but uh it may happen
in the coming days so these are the ways
that that is typically how you
bring down a country like you say or
make a country Surrender by taking over
all the infrastructure Communications
infrastructure uh Transportation
infrastructure all the entry exit points
all the broadcasting infrastructure and
eventually all the important people you
captured them so that's how a country is
captured and the regime is changed
that's how it's done
actually says how long the planning must
have taken for this kind of invasion and
another question
and does India have okay let's let's not
go into India yet
how long do you think the planning took
for this kind of invasion that is a very
good question once again I like the
questions people are asking
so
back to the map
the Russian invasion and annexation
of Crimea happened in 2014
and it was a very Swift move
so clearly even that had been planned in
advance right so if so typically you
would need at least minimum six months
to plan an invasion occupation and
annexation you want to make it as quick
as possible as smooth as possible you
want to encounter the least possible
resistance
the best way of winning is to is to win
without any resistance at all it should
not even look like you have spent any
effort that is the best way of winning
without suffering any losses any
casualties of of men or material so The
Invasion and occupation and annexation
of Crimea was very Swift it was very
smooth so clearly that was planned in
advance so the planning must have
happened at least I would say a couple
of years before 2014 so let's say 2012.
and when the planning for the annexation
of Crimea was happening I can assure you
that
the Soviet uh the the sorry not so with
the Russian military must already have
had contingency plans in place of how to
take over parts of Ukraine if the need
arises and obviously the need arose in
2014 when the regime was changed
illegally and democratically so I would
say that the Russians have been planning
I would imagine I don't have I am not
privy to actual information I am I'm not
privy to any actual real information I
am guessing I'm guessing Okay this is
this is just conjecture I am guessing
that the Russians have been planning the
invasion of Ukraine since 2014.
Mr Putin must have given instructions
orders to his army to the to his
generals to his planners strategic
planners tactical planners to draw out
detailed Innovation plans of Ukraine and
all the pieces on the chessboard were
slowly step by step systematically put
in place
over the time over the years and finally
when Mr Putin calculated that the time
is right he has gone ahead with the
invasion and as you can see the invasion
is being
executed very systematically they are
avoiding any unnecessary military action
you will see that civilians are able to
stand in their windows and take videos
of the fighting that's happening which
means civilians are completely safe they
are not touching civilians they are
doing what you can call surgical
military strikes airports they're
controlling the highways like I said how
to take over a country they're doing
precisely that so it's very well planned
and it's being executed very well so I
think it's it's been in the planning
since 2014. you have to plan you cannot
just say oh today I feel like invading
let's go invade that's not how it's done
that's the short short way of losing
okay Rahul says what is Pakistan's play
in all this uh why did
why did Imran Khan visit Moscow on the
eve of the Ukrainian Invasion are they
secretly or not secretly allying and
does this also in turn Aid Pakistan in
annexing territories
okay let me explain the role of Mr Imran
Khan in all of this Mr Imran Khan was
used as a smoke screen by Mr Putin
so Mr Putin must have decided when he
was going to invade right so he invited
Mr Imran Khan to to to his country one
day before that so the so in the eyes of
the world it will look like a foreign
prime minister has come to Russia so
clearly Russia will not make any silly
moves at this time when when a foreign
head of state is visiting right Mr Putin
will be busy meeting Mr um Khan and and
giving him his Hospitality making maybe
maybe signing agreements and all that
obviously Invasion will not happen at
the time but what happened is that
precisely when Mr Imran Khan came the
invasion was launched so Mr Imran Khan's
visit was used as a smoke screen to
divert the rest of the world
Mr Imran Khan was used as a diversionary
tactic and I believe the meeting between
him and Mr Putin lasted all of five
minutes it was just for the photo
opportunity nothing else you could see
you could see people stay around Khan's
face
it was a very long phase it was a long
phase anyway it was even longer when you
missed the Putin
and Mr Putin said the welcome Mr Prime
Minister in in English
shook his hand they sat down for a
couple of minutes and then the photo op
was over and then it will be end of the
story because Mr Putin has more
important things to take care of there's
an invasion going on
so Mr Imran Khan's visit was completely
pointless fruitless from his perspective
from Mr Putin's perspective he served a
useful purpose he's in he's a useful
idiot who was used and then discarded
okay there is no secret Alliance
happening between Russia and Pakistan
there is no annexation which will happen
none of that
so the only purpose that Mr Imran Khan's
visit served in Moscow was to camouflage
The Invasion that's all it was
aradhana says what are the what were the
factors for the Ukrainian Army laying
down arms and fleeing off within hours
of the invasion are ukrainians patriotic
people and so on and how many Ukrainian
people wish to rejoin Russia so the
invasion is still proceeding it's
proceeding very systematically
uh
the amount of resistance that has been
met has not been significant yes there
are some casualties on both sides I
don't know how many ukrainians Ukrainian
soldiers may have died uh the Western
media is reporting that 200 300 Russian
soldiers have died well that's War if
even if it is true that's part of
warfare right
Warfare is not all
it's not it's not roses it's not fun and
games it's very serious it's deadly
serious so
I would not say that ukrainians have
completely completely laid down their
arms and fled but the Russians are
making
steady progress uh if they want they can
capture Ukraine in the next half an hour
they can just obliterate it with their
bombers they are choosing not to do it
they are proceeding very carefully they
the main thing is they want to avoid all
unnecessary casualties they don't touch
a single civilian they want to do it as
painlessly as possible otherwise Ukraine
would have been finished by now if the
Russians had if Mr Putin had ordered its
heavy bombers to just blast the city of
Kiev it would be over within the within
the first 60 minutes but that's not what
he has done right so uh I am still not
quite sure what is the objective does Mr
Putin intend to take over the entirety
of Ukraine or is he just
uh is the objective just to take over
the eastern part of Ukraine donbass and
adjoining regions and effect a regime
change in Kiev
so we still don't know we still not have
Clarity most likely
see it is a Fool's errand to make
predictions right as I know very well
but most likely I think Mr Putin may not
want to as of right now take over the
whole of Ukraine
he will he is doing this shock and O
Campaign which is which has scared the
ukrainians uh they may surrender sooner
sooner or later and then the regime
change will happen in Kiev a pro-russia
president will be installed the way the
westerners installed somebody else was
Pro West
and maybe that pro-russian President
Will You Will Rule you Ukraine as a de
facto Russian puppet so that is also
something that could be
in the works so we don't know yet what
the intentions are what's clear is that
the eastern part of Ukraine will become
part of Russia or it will be recognized
as independent territories which are
more or less under Russian control so
the situation is still fluid we don't
have significant Clarity yet by Design
when you invade when you go to war you
make sure the enemy has no clarity as to
what your true intentions are you have
to disguise your intentions all Warfare
is based on Deception
so that's what we are seeing right now
so let's see how this goes
okay dhruv says if Ukraine becomes a
part of Russia do you think how do you
think the civilians will react to it
would they have any say you know at all
in the future will it come like another
Tibet
you know
I don't know who it is who said this
the weak do what they will
and no sorry sorry not the week I got it
backwards the strong do what they will
and the weak must suffer as they must
that's how it goes what do the Ukrainian
civilians have to do with this nothing
how will they react to it they will have
to swallow their pride and accept the
new circumstances
right anyway they were part of the USSR
it was all mainly run by Russians
so it's not something that's new for
them they are also not some separate
culture separate ethnicity separate race
or anything they are they are Slavic
people just like the Russians it's a
very similar culture the language is
very similar the Customs are very
similar the culture is very similar so
it's not going to be something
significantly different there won't be a
very big change
for the Ukrainian civilians some of them
will not be happy with it some of them
will say well so what life goes on and
so on so the Ukrainian civilians will
not have much of a say in any of this
right democracy is a nice thing to talk
about but there is no real democracy
anywhere in the world even in the
Western countries the so-called liberal
democracies as we can see these days
right so Ukraine will not become another
Tibet uh in Tibet what you think is
complete cultural genocide Tibetan
culture has been Stamped Out the only
place where Tibetan culture really
survives is in India
in Tibet you're not even allowed to
children are not even allowed to study
in their mother tongue they are made to
study all the all their education is in
Chinese in India it's all in Indian uh
it's all in English so we are also in in
a way colonized anyway that's a
different story so Ukraine will not
become like another Tibet it will become
the way Ukraine was under the USSR kind
of if Mr Putin chooses to take over the
whole of Ukraine or otherwise it may
become the western part of Ukraine may
become a puppet state a satellite state
of Russia
so that remains to be seen But the
Ukrainian civilians have no say in what
happens none whatsoever
okay two questions uh ahan says what Han
says could Russia try expanding more
into Eastern Europe by attacking Moldova
especially since Russia and Moldova are
in opposing sides in the transnet Square
dispute abhi says greetings for problem
from Poland taking into consideration
that Putin might actually capture the
whole of Ukraine what might be his next
move will he dare attack the Baltic
countries is they used to be within the
USSR or dare to attack Poland as it is
next to Ukraine good question let's look
at these countries Moldova
and so on uh let's go to the map
so the countries he's referring to let's
go let's zoom out Belarus is now under
Russian control whether you like it or
not Moldova was it's over here
south west of Ukraine it was part of the
USSR
right and west of Ukraine west of
Belarus you have Poland and the Baltic
states
that were referred to are Estonia Latvia
and Lithuania and this is khalidine grad
which is Russian territory it's a it's a
Russian exclave
so the question
is with reference to these territories
what is going to happen next could
Russia try expanding into Eastern Europe
which means
Lithuania Latvia
Estonia Poland Romania Moldova Bulgaria
and so on
is is that what's going to happen
and uh what ABY is saying will Mr Putin
attack Poland I don't think Mr Putin has
gone mad
I think Mr Putin is a very rational
person
what he is doing is not craziness it's
not Madness it is something that has
been long in the planning
and he has calculated precisely
how far he can go
with this Invasion he has calculated
correctly that NATO will not intervene
and try to save Ukraine even though they
have promised the moon and the stars to
Ukraine and yet they have abandoned
Ukraine in his time of need so Mr Putin
calculated that correctly
but
Mr Putin is not Adolf Hitler Adolf
Hitler had gone mad with ambition
the more territories he conquered the
more his Ambitions grew the more his
greed grew right Mr Putin is unlikely to
make such a mistake
I do not believe Mr Putin will go beyond
Belarus and Ukraine I do not think he
will go into Moldova yet I do not
believe he will go into Lithuania Latvia
Estonia yet maybe 10 years in the future
when things are significantly different
he may entertain such plans I don't
think it's going to happen in 2022. and
I don't think he's going to make a move
a military move on Poland like I said
the best way of fighting of the best way
of winning a war is to win the war
without firing a single bullet that is
the best way of winning a war so if you
can
coerce and bully a country
and carry out a regime change and
install a puppet regime that is
pro-russia then why do you need to go to
war and you can engineer that over time
in a few years without ever spending
military might in doing that
so there are multiple ways of achieving
your objectives war is typically the
last alternative it's the last recourse
right so the NATO actions pushed Mr
Putin into a certain spot and then based
on those calculations he decided to
take military action but for Poland for
for Moldova he doesn't need to take
military action look at look at Belarus
like I said Belarus is now more or less
under Russian control did you have to
send his army there to to achieve this
military control uh to achieve political
control no
all he had to do was make sure that the
president of Belarus changes the
Constitution which makes Belarus more or
less de facto a russian-controlled
nation
right so Belarus is more or less no
longer a sovereign state and it's fine
that's what they want
so he was able to achieve that without
fighting a single bullet so is that not
a superior way of achieving your
objectives
so I would say that Mr Putin is unlikely
at least in 2022 of trying to invade
Putin uh Poland or any other state it
would be unwise to do that he would risk
getting overstretched and I don't think
the Chinese would like that either of
this behaving in such a manner and I
don't think Mr Putin is greedy the way
Adolf Hitler was greedy so I think it's
unlikely
osmitha says the U.S has indicated it
will not send troops to Ukraine what
options does the U.S have to make
Russians withdraw
without crossing the margin of safety
I'm sure the economic sanctions are
anticipated by the Russians they must be
having a plan to deal with them and Saha
says what are the substantial
repercussions that Russia can face in
the coming days and how badly can they
affect Russia in the long run
so what the Americans can do is they can
cut off Russia's access to Netflix
to Disney plus to HBO
and they can
they can perhaps cut off Russia's access
to the Swift banking system and they can
they have already imposed various uh
economic sanctions on Russia because
currently the global economy is
controlled by the US
yeah it's controlled by the US
there's no other way of putting it so
they can cut off various countries from
the system if they wish to so that's
what they're doing so like you said
Smitha that there are the Mr Putin was
and he knew this is what's going to
happen
he must have anticipated even further
moves from the economic front
so that was anticipated what options
does the U.S have to make the Russians
withdraw without crossing the margin of
safety no options
the Americans are not going to be able
to make the versions withdraw what they
could do is they could foment in
Afghanistan style Insurgency in Ukraine
which will destroy the country
if they do that let's go to the map
if the Americans do that
they will have to do it via Romania or
Hungary or Slovakia or Poland
and I doubt very much if these countries
want to come on the bad side of Russia
if they allow the Americans to funnel
arms ammunition weapons and Personnel
across their borders into Ukraine to
create to create an Insurgency
they're gonna face adverse repercussions
from the Russians I don't think anybody
wants that right now right but what the
Americans can do especially if the
Russians don't take over the whole of
Ukraine is they can ferment some kind of
Insurgency in Ukraine incidences are
terrible in the 1980s they did this in
Afghanistan via Pakistan they use the
Pakistani isi and the Pakistani
government under the al-haq to funnel
arms ammunition terrorists uh sorry
Freedom Fighters into Afghanistan
which eventually led to the defeat of
the USSR in 1989 and 88 18 and whatever
whichever year it was
so they could try that in Ukraine but I
I'm not sure how much that would work
because Ukraine is not Afghanistan
and if they do it it's it would be a
very cynical and sad thing to do because
it will destroy the country it will
cause all kinds of Civilian casualties
but the Americans may do that they may
explore that option because they don't
care about anyone's any civilians as
their track record proves
okay next
ritesh says does Russia's invasion of
Ukraine show that whenever a big country
will want it will occupy and engulf
smaller countries what will happen to
the world order then how will the world
run
this is the way the world order has
always run
it's always been this way
you may be under the impression my dear
friends that we have what the Americans
called a rules-based global order
there are what are the rules show me the
rules where do we find the written rules
there are no written rules
whatever they say is the rules for now
right now next week they will make a
different set of rules right now they
are bombing Yemen into the Dust
they are killing civilians every day
where are the rules
where are human rights
right
they can invade any country the world
they want and call it liberation
see what happened in Libya North Africa
do you know where Libya is uh the
Americans liberated Libya
see Libya is here Muammar Gaddafi was
the ruler of Libya where is Libya here
it is
North Africa in the context of the world
here is Libya so the Americans liberated
this in the early 2010s was it 2010-11
something like that right
they liberated Libya brought in
democracy apparently and soon after that
what you saw in Libya was open slave
markets
and what happened to Human Rights then
why did the Americans not stop it
foreign
slave markets in Libya and the same
thing was happening in Syria when the
Americans were trying to liberate Syria
right and the same thing was happening
in Iraq after the Americans liberated
Iraq
so when they invade when they take over
a country it's called liberation
and then the world order Remains the
Same it remains fine because they are
doing it but when Russia does it oh my
goodness the world order is unbalanced
Save the rules-based World Order what
hypocrisy is this so you know what my my
dear friend ritesh the world order has
always been this way
the world order runs on the basis of
geopolitics there are no friendships or
alliances in geopolitics the only
consideration in geopolitics is
self-interest
I will do what I can I will try and get
away with as much as I can at the
expense of everybody else
there are no friendships there are no
principles the only principle is power
and strength if I am strong enough I can
do it if you had asked Julius Caesar why
did you conquer he would have given
given you a straightforward answer I
conquer because I can
that's how the world has always run all
this world order liberal democracy
rules-based system is a myth it's just
slogans
so the world will run just fine it's
always been this way
right I mean look at India the Chinese
took over part of oxide part of ladakh
called accepting the the the the
pakistanis took over Pok if you are weak
this will keep happening
it's going to keep happening that's just
how the way the way the world runs
okay next Aditi says isn't it a great
shame for the US it failed to protect
the country that always adored its model
and was low-key in its sphere of
influence
does this indicate the rising impotency
in biden-led USA
good question
the Americans encouraged the ukrainians
to become very strongly anti-russia
right they they promised the sun and the
moon and the stars to the ukrainians
and when Mr Putin
has given the order for the invasion
where are the Americans
right and the the excuse the Americans
are giving is that Ukraine is not part
of NATO so we are not Duty bound or or
treaty bound to come and save the
ukrainians so that's why we will just
watch while this happens and that is
what Mr Putin had correctly calculated
that the Americans will abandon the
ukrainians in their time of need
Mr Putin knew it because the Americans
have a track record of abandoning
everybody
right
so
so is it a great shame for the U.S well
the U.S does it doesn't worry about
shame and we know what's interesting
the Americans have issued a travel
advisory in which they have stated in
writing that they will not evacuate
American citizens from Ukraine we will
not be doing that and look at India
India is doing everything it can it is
sending planes Air India planes into a
war zone to bring back its citizens from
this war zone India is doing everything
it can to bring back its citizens from
from Ukraine and the Americans have said
it
you can look it up online they travel
advisory from the U.S state Department
we will not bring back U.S citizens from
Ukraine deal with it you are on your own
you're abandoned so if they don't even
care about their own citizens what do
you think they'll care for Ukraine right
so what we are witnessing right now
is the beginning of the end of Western
Supremacy in the world this is the
visible this is this point
2022 the Russian invasion of Ukraine is
going to go down in history as the
beginning of the decline of the Western
World of the western Supremacy over the
world
it they still control the global economy
the U.S is still a superpower they can
still intervene anywhere in the world
militarily at 60 minutes notice they can
do it but they are a declining power we
are seeing it as visible right now
so yes you can you can say that it
indicates the rising importance of
biden-led USA it's all about leadership
they have lost the plot they have when
was the last time the U.S had a strong
leader
I can't think of a single strong leader
in the U.S since Ronald Reagan
now
1978 no sorry 1980 to 88 I think he was
in power
so after Ronald Reagan every single U.S
president has been
you know nothing great nothing special
and if you look at Mr Biden right now
the less we say about him the better
so yes we are witnessing in real time
the decline of the West and they are
going to get more and more vindictively
as their power declines
we're gonna see that
Soul Tunes says as you mentioned there
there are many countries that want to
regain their old Empire status like
Russia turkey China even India that
requires interference in another
sovereign country my question is how do
these countries justify their actions
and secondly how are India's Ambitions
different from these other Imperials
powers
India has no stated ambitions
you have never you will never see an
Indian
leader an Indian Prime Minister
President defense minister or anybody
ever saying that India has Imperial
ambitions and you have not seen you have
not witnessed a single Indian leader
having said such a such a thing in the
last hundred years
so India has no such stated Ambitions
India has no Imperial ambitions
that needs to be reiterated
show me a single instance of an Indian
leader
saying that India wants to take over
other countries
you will not see that right
okay now well the the thing that is
asked over here is that many countries
want to do this they have Imperial
Ambitions which requires interference in
other Sovereign countries how do these
countries justify the actions there is
no need to justify it might is right to
the America yeah you can you can talk
about uh principles and all that like
the Americans always say we are bringing
democracy we believe in a rules-based
order Global Order when somebody is
acting badly Behaving Badly we will go
and reimpose democracy there so that is
the justification of the pretext for
invading countries and destroying
countries right so that is the American
model that you first take the moral High
Ground you talk about democracy you talk
about Liberal Liberal democracy you talk
about the human rights
even though you are violating all these
things but you use the right words and
then you invade so you first take the
moral High Ground you justify your
Invasion based on that moral High Ground
that you've taken and then you invade so
the Russians if you if you see Mr
Putin's speech before he ordered the
invasion
he issued a justification of why he is
doing this that this is all historically
Russian territory and you know what if
you study the history of the region you
will find that he was right this was
historically all Russian territory for
centuries right so there are all kinds
of justifications you can issue but at
the end of the day
in geopolitics might is right so you
don't necessarily need to issue
justifications right and there is no
right or wrong in geopolitics please
understand this Indians have this great
hang up
things have to be justified you can't do
certain things it's immoral unethical to
do certain things
that applies only to India apparently
everybody else can do what they want but
if India does something it's unethical
it is unjustified you know what there is
no such thing as right or wrong in
geopolitics if you can do it you do it
that's just the way the world Works look
at the past 1000 years of Indian history
right everybody came and took whatever
they wanted
four thousand years that's why India is
such a broken down
country that's why the economy is so
small because they stole all our wealth
and all that wealth that was stolen from
India
hundreds of trillions of dollars of
worth of wealth was stolen from India it
is currently in the West
the West has grown at India's expense
so in the future if India where
hypothetically to Harbor Imperial
Ambitions who can blame India for that
right
I'm not saying India should do it or
India has any such Ambitions I'm just
saying if hypothetically India were in
the future to develop such Ambitions who
is anybody to show us the should talk
about human rights and all that ethics
and morality there is no ethics more
Morality In geopolitics as we can see
okay now we come to the main thing which
side should we go on as a country with
Ukraine or Russia
Taiwan which will be important to us is
the future is supporting Ukraine there's
no reason for us to support Ukraine is
it right to remain neutral uh what
should India do essentially in this
situation will while we definitely can't
get get on the bad side of Russia being
neutral doesn't seem to be an option why
why what would be the best way for us to
deal with this
see it's very simple very very very
simple which which
side should India be on is the question
this is a very good question it's a very
important question which side should
India take in this conflict and the
answer I'm gonna give you is very simple
India should take
India's side India should do whatever it
is needed
to further India's national interest
whatever is in our best interests we
should do it so right now as you can see
in the UN India abstained from the
devote condemning Russian actions
India issued a set of reasons why it is
abstaining but the real deal is this
that India doesn't see any
justification in opposing Russian the
Russian action
and it is better for India not to get on
the bad side of Russia because we have a
lot in common
and we are going to have much more in
common in the coming years and decades
our national interests align
significantly
right and the Russians have a track
record of being on India's side for
whatever reason they are doing it out of
their own self into sure
but they still have a track record of
being a reliable partner if you look at
look back at the last 60 70 80 years
and what is America's track record
they supplied Pakistan with the Weaponry
with the ammunition with the training
and billions of dollars per year for
decades
and they used Pakistan as a proxy to
bleed India
that's what the Americans did
what happened in 2008 when the
pakistanis stormed the city of Bombay
they they held the city of Bombay
hostage and killed hundreds of people
did the Americans impose sanctions on
Pakistan did they bomb Pakistan no
what happened when the Chinese did the
Galvan misadventure in the killed Indian
soldiers did the West
condemn Chinese actions did they impose
sanctions on China was there a vote in
the U.N for condemning the Chinese
action nothing they urged both sides to
resolve the matter through talks please
don't resort to violence please exercise
restraint
they have never supported India so why
should India support Ukraine or the West
the ukrainians have always voted against
India in the U.N
they voted to impose sanctions on India
in 1998.
when India did conducted the nuclear
tests right
and they have been supplying the
pakistanis with weaponry and various uh
military material which is used against
India and now they want India's help
now they are holding our students
hostage and blackmailing India openly
on the United Nations security Council
stage
why would India support Ukraine
the sooner Mr Putin takes over the
better for us that will free our
students there
so India
should take India's side and it is best
for India's long-term National interest
to stay out of this matter and some
people are saying some Geniuses in the
media are saying that India has gone
back to non-alignment because India is
abstain from the vote India did not take
the side of the west or of Russia
India abstain so this is non-alignment
these people who say that are real
geniuses I must applaud their Brilliance
if they call this non-alignment
non-alignment which comes from the
nairobian times was a totally different
thing it was about
hurting your National interest what
India is doing is in the pursuance of
its long-term natural interest what
India did right now abstaining from
voting that is the right strategy it is
not
non-alignment it is actually
non-alignment with the West a vote to
abstain is actually a vote in favor of
Russia in the current situation and
circumstances what the U.S and the West
wanted to achieve in the U.N vote was to
say that the the majority of the world
stands with Ukraine if India had voted
against Russia
that would add 1.3 billion votes against
Russia then they could claim that the
majority of the world is against Russia
but by abstaining we have defeated that
move
so India essentially is standing with
Russia and not with the West
so that's what India is doing stay
neutral doesn't seem to be an option Why
by
we are not neutral
we are technically neutral but we are on
our own side we are doing what is best
for us in the long run we're gonna need
Russia
we are going to need Russia in the long
long run what do the Americans people
say that India is part of the Quad India
is part of the U.S led grouping so India
should remain loyal to the quad in the
U.S why why why why what does India get
from staying loyal or being loyal to the
US do we get something from the U.S do
we get some special
weapon systems do we get some transfer
of Technology
do we get some economic benefits we get
nothing
and look at our cooperation with Russia
we they are helping us develop
miniaturized nuclear reactors to be used
in nuclear submarines
they are helping us with our nuclear
submarine design they have always helped
us with various other weapons and
Technologies
they transferred the mig-21 technology
it was in the 1960s we never use that
that's a different story right
and our cooperation with them is is
still very significant more than 60 70
of our weapons purchases still come from
from Russia why should we vote against
them
give me one single good reason for that
right
so we are not voting for them or against
them we are just staying technically
neutral which is something that is
really infuriated the West right now and
we are seeing that on social media all
their disposable freelance minions are
tweeting
on Twitter
and trying to portray India's actions as
as being in favor of Russia so that's
what we are seeing right now
okay shankajit says since Russia
willingly formed alliances with India's
Force like China and Pakistan why
shouldn't India take the side of the U.S
in 30 NATO countries plus Australia and
New Zealand
in exchange for good perks okay good
argument just tell me what good perk is
India getting name a single good perk
that India is getting from the West
I'll wait
I'm listening name a single good perk
are we getting some weapons system are
we getting any transfer of Technology
are they giving us nuclear reactor
designs for submarines are they giving
us anything they're giving us nothing
and Russia has not entered a formal
alliance with China and let alone
Pakistan Pakistan is nothing it's it's a
disposable convenient state to be used
and thrown away
the Russians have not formed an alliance
with China it's not a formal alliance
yes there is systemic coordination and
cooperation between Russia and China and
they are doing it because of their
self-interest they have to the Americans
are hell-bent on destroying Russia
uprooting it from the foundations so
they are
for the sake of convenience right now
temporarily cooperating with China
because the economic sanctions otherwise
would destroy Russia the Chinese are
willing to finance Russia fund Russia so
that insulates the Russians to some
extent from the economic sanctions and
the Chinese get
a big strong power that is willing to
act as a mercenary for them so this is a
temporary situation it's not going to
persist forever
if Russia becomes stronger the Chinese
will feel threatened if China becomes
stronger the Russians will will feel
threatened do you know why let me
demonstrate why look at the map
look at the border how long the border
is between Russia and China
thousands of kilometers you have a
border here which is a few hundred
kilometers
and you have another border here
very long border and this Border in
Manchuria has historically been disputed
the Chinese claim large parts of
the Russian Far East
right
and they did sign a boundary agreement
uh I think it is in the 1990s 2000s
maybe look it up I don't remember the
date exactly some somewhere around that
time so the boundary dispute has been
settled between China and Russia but
from the Russian perspective
I would urge you to watch my
conversation with Dr Edward luthwork so
he says that from the Russian
perspective the boundary dispute is not
settled it is merely dormant the Chinese
will reopen the boundary dispute at the
appropriate time so the Russians know
that they don't see China as a long-term
Ally in the 1960s Russia and China went
to war nearly went to war there were
very significant border clashes hundreds
of soldiers died
there was even hand-to-hand combat like
we have these days with the Chinese
and the Russians nearly
the Russians nearly nuked China and who
prevented
the USSR from nuking China
it was the United States and that is the
beginning between the beginning of the
alliance between us and China and the
Americans for some reason aided and
abetted the rise of China
they created the biggest monster they
have ever seen
so that's some history so Russia doesn't
have an alliance with China the Russians
know very well that China is their
biggest long-term threat and that is the
reason why India and Russia are
long-term Partners whether they call it
an official Alliance or not we are
allies
and the West will not help us tomorrow
if China invades India the Americans are
not going to help India
so why should India take the child take
the side of the U.S or NATO
they have never taken our side ever
okay
um
was it really a good move by Russia or
was it really necessary and should India
be a mediator in this for Ukraine
given that in the past during our
nuclear test they condemned us gave T20
tanks to Pakistan recently upgraded
those thanks for Pakistan even when
India requested them not to do so and
now they are pleading with us with two
sugar-coated words Russia is still way
more important for us so you have
answered your question
India does not need to be a mediator
India does not need to take the side of
Ukraine or the west or NATO
the ukrainians have always been
anti-india as you have stated over here
very clearly the West has always been
into India even today they are very into
India this is simply using India as a
Pawn on the geopolitical chess board to
offset and counter balance China to some
extent so that's the only utility that
India has for the U.S right now
that's the only reason
they are playing nice to some extent
with India
if the Chinese threat goes away they
will want to destroy India as well per
the Blitzer Doctrine the Americans have
a very
less known Doctrine called the Blitzer
Doctrine not the Blitzkrieg Doctrine the
Blitzer Doctrine
you will not find any reference to this
anywhere and this Doctrine says that any
country that can potentially in the
future be a threat to the U.S maybe 10
20 50 years on the line that country
should be crippled or destroyed
so that's what they are doing against
Russia they're trying to destroy Russia
and if India were to start Rising Beyond
an economy of five trillion or so they
may do the same with India also
India doesn't need to take the side of
the West the US Ukraine
the question is was it really a good
move by Russia or really necessary I
think it was necessary otherwise Ukraine
would have become a part of NATO which
would mean that you would have American
nuclear weapons right at the border with
Ukraine that is an unacceptable threat
for Russia
so they it was a necessary move was it a
good move it's been a good move what has
what repercussions has Russia faced
apart from economic sanctions which they
had already anticipated
the Americans have not got involved in
Ukraine they have not come to save
Ukraine so it was a good move yes well
calculated move very well calculated
calculated move
uh given that India has maintained
continued silence on the Russian
invasion of Ukraine does India need to
intervene diplomatically or militarily
if China sets its look on Taiwan how
should we approach that issue now Taiwan
is a whole different story
India officially doesn't have diplomatic
relations relations with Taiwan India
in a way adheres to the so-called One
China policy because India is not yet
strong enough to counter China so right
now we're just abiding for time India is
slowly Rising growing let's see how
quickly we can do that in case
the Chinese decide to invade Taiwan
there's not much India can do about it
India cannot do anything diplomatically
yeah India can protest
diplomatically India could move a
resolution in the U.N or support or move
in the U.N to condemn Chinese actions
and so on that India can do yes
diplomatically but that really amounts
to nothing much the U.N is a toothless
powerless body
in the true sense of the world what can
India do militarily India can't do
anything militarily
against China in the defense of Taiwan
because our Navy isn't that big that we
can have a significant presence in the
so-called South China Sea or which is
actually the champasi the champasi what
should India do then if the Chinese were
to invade Taiwan or God forbid capture
Taiwan what should India do it's very
simple many people will not like what I
say what India should do is it should
immediately if the Chinese make a move
on Taiwan India should immediately
without losing even a minute
India should immediately secure Nepal
and Sri Lanka
that's what India should do I hope the
plans have been made
India should immediately secure you can
interpret that word secure in any way
you want I'm gonna use the word secure
India should immediately secure Nepal
and Sri Lanka if the Chinese make a move
on Taiwan
that's what India should do and listen
if my Nepalese friends are watching I am
not anti-nepal I am Pro Nepal we are the
same people
I have I I am very fond of The Nepalese
people of The Nepalese culture of all of
that and India needs to protect Nepal
from China
that's what needs to happen so if the
Chinese make a move on Taiwan India must
secure Nepal and the same goes for Sri
Lanka
uh Sandeep says will China take
advantage of the situation to escalate
tensions On the indo-china Border or to
attack Taiwan as the whole attention is
currently on the Russia Ukraine war yes
very good point Sandeep uh I am not sure
about whether China would want to attack
Taiwan right now maybe it is not yet
time for them to do that
the Americans have a very significant
presence in on Taiwanese soil itself so
if the Chinese were to invade Taiwan it
would be an attack on America itself and
the Americans are treaty bound with
Taiwan to defend Taiwan so that could
become a big conflagration I don't think
the Chinese already ready for that yet
but they can certainly
escalate tensions on the India Tibet
border yes so India must be ready for
this India must be prepared
after what's happening in Ukraine the
Chinese will start
upping the ante I believe it is possible
it is likely that they will start
creating more problems on the India
Tibet border Chinese occupied Tibet so
you could see more clashes you could see
more incursions by the Chinese into
Indian Territory
that is something that is likely to
happen in the coming days weeks months
quite possible so India needs to be
prepared for that and India needs to in
my opinion now I think it is time now
for India
to enhance its military budget the world
has changed
the West is declining
the West is not going to come to India's
Aid if things go south if hostilities
break out with China
yes we have a nuclear umbrella we have a
nuclear deterrent we need to build more
Agni five nuclear missiles we need to
build a few more nuclear warheads keep
them ready
and
we need to increase the military budget
it is time for that right now I'm not
sure what the military budget is maybe
two percent of the Indian economy of the
Indian annual GDP I'm not sure what it
is I don't have the exact figures I
think it's time to double the budget
India needs to do that let's see what
the government decides but I think it is
the world is changed now and we have to
move accordingly
Aman says if this war were to spiral
into a global conflict or simply
increase Global tensions how prepare is
prepared is India economically and in
terms of its defense will India be able
to endure such a tense scenario between
the world powers
especially in the post-covered recovery
phase and chiching asks
if in the future China and Pakistan
decide to invade Kashmir radak or
arunachal Pradesh will India be able to
defend itself without any address help I
think India is
India has been preparing for a two-front
war for a long time India is very very
well aware of what can happen a
simultaneous uh
simultaneous attack by China and
Pakistan coordinated attack on two
flanks by Pakistan in the Kashmir region
in the Gujarat Rajasthan region and the
Chinese from Tibet and arunachal this
could happen yes and I believe India has
been planning for such an eventuality
and there are certain red lines that the
Chinese will be aware of
and if those Redlands across India can
take any any action in its defense and
when I mean any action
we know what any action means
we have the first we have the no first
use nuclear policy which means that we
will not use nuclear weapons first but
hey words are words
actions can be different
so I believe that India is reasonably
prepared
I think if the Chinese or the pakistanis
were to cross a certain line they would
be made to pay very badly
if the pakistanis across a certain line
Pakistan will essentially cease to exist
as a nation as a people
and similarly for the Chinese if there
is a certain line they cross we have the
final deterrent and I think our Armed
Forces our armed forces are also
reasonably well prepared uh we have good
infrastructure
a reasonably good equipment and all that
so I think as of today we are reasonably
well prepared for such an eventuality a
two front a two or two flank War
but like I said I think it is now time
for India to completely re-evaluate
its military policy and plans I think it
is time for India to double the military
budget
to incorporate more nuclear missiles
nuclear warheads and India needs a
significantly
more powerful navy
I am not saying build more aircraft
carriers which is which is lunacy India
doesn't need more aircraft carriers
India needs
distributed lethality in the Indian
Ocean
quantity has a quality of its own India
needs numbers when I mean when I say
numbers I mean more missiles the
strength of your Navy
is measured in the number of missiles
you can deploy at Sea on any given day
in a distributed manner if you have
three big ships with 300 missiles each
they can be easily taken care of but if
you have 200 ships with three missiles
each that is a whole different order of
threat that's what India needs to do
India right now not prepared on the
naval front but we are not going to face
an invasion from C right now we are
reasonably well prepared on the land
borders with China and Tibet or with
Pakistan in Tibet but we need to prepare
for them so this is a very good question
says what is the best thing for India to
do support
USA and the NATO support Russia or stay
neutral and silently take control of Pok
so the first two scenarios I have to I
have addressed the question is should
India silently take control of p.o.k
Pakistan occupied Kashmir
should India do that that would involve
retaking Pakistan occupied Kashmir would
involve military Maneuvers it would
involve crossing the line of actual
control with tanks with Soldiers with
with the Air Force possibly
that can lead to a chain reaction
India doesn't want a chain reaction
at this point
right now what India wants to do is to
keep things under control
what India wants to do is to become a 10
trillion dollar economy at the as soon
as possible right now we are merely a
three trillion dollar economy we have a
long way to go we cannot afford to go to
war right now
trying to take Pok right now could
escalate when the shooting starts you're
no longer in control this is one of the
principles of warfare you can make them
all kinds of plans but the moment the
firing the shooting starts all plans go
out of the window anything can happen
any kind of escalation any kind of chain
reaction can happen right now we don't
want that
we have to wait another decade at least
patience my dear friends patience we
will take be okay we will take it I
promise you that but not yet
not yet have some more patience we will
do it
but this is not the right time
okay Krishna says looking at the
situation what is a what is the chance
of India trying for akhanda Bharat
will it be in our national interest at
this point in time what will be the
steps for it
like I said we can't even take yoga
right now
we can we can't take it but it may lead
to consequences that are beyond our
control right now the only thing we need
is a larger economy why do I keep on
talking about a 10 trillion dollar
economy it's because your military
budget is always proportional to the
size of your economy
if we had a three times larger economy
today nine trillion dollars then our
military budget would be three times
greater than what it is today
right
so if India becomes a 10 trillion dollar
economy India will become a military
superpower
right now we cannot become a military
support power because we don't have the
funds we don't have sufficient funds we
have sufficient funds to take care of
our defense and impose unacceptable
costs for any misadventure by China or
Pakistan but we still don't have the
funds to become a genuine
Global level military power we don't
have it or or even Regional level power
so
the steps the first step for India
is to become a much bigger economy we
have to industrialize we have to grow at
10 plus every year anyhow no excuses the
government needs to find ways of doing
it for the next 10 15 maybe 20 years we
need to keep our profile low keep our
heads down and work as hard as we can
and build the economy and when the time
is right we'll take back the okay
and we will liberate Tibet
and I think
beyond that let's let's not think about
anything beyond that because the true
the solution to Pok is actually Tibet
the reason why the pakistanis are so
gung-ho and strong is because they
currently have a common border with with
the Chinese occupied territories in
Tibet
and that's why the Chinese can supply
them anytime and that's why the Chinese
can even send troops to Pakistan's
rescue if they want
so if we cut off Pakistan's access to
the Chinese supply lines and Supply
chains and soldiers and all that then we
can deal with the pakistanis and be okay
and we can fragment Pakistan in the long
run so the so the real solution is to
stop obsessing about Pok the solution to
poke lies in Tibet but India is in no
position of even dreaming
of liberating Tibet right now so we have
to put ourselves in a position to be
able to do that it's gonna take at least
10 years so the steps for creating what
you call akand Bharat is to work very
hard for the next 10 20 years become a
significantly larger economy minimum 10
trillion dollars and develop a
proportionately large militarily
military
then what you call akand Bharat
maybe within the realm of possibility
so we need patience my friends we will
do it we will take back the okay we will
liberate Tibet but this is not the right
time it is going to happen within our
lifetimes but not yet
okay two more two three more questions
uh shankajit says
if India continues to purchase the
Russian military machinery
then going forward is there a chance
that the U.S will impose katsa sanctions
on India if that happens then what
should India do between America and NATO
and Russia which side should India align
with uh what is katsa you may ask
so let us go into what katsa is let us
um
let us Google cats are
what is katsa
here's Google
c-a-a-t-s-a katsa
so it means countering America's
adversaries through sanctions Act
so what it means is that if you were to
purchase weapons
from
a country that the Americans considered
to be an enemy they can impose sanctions
on you that's what katsa means
now the Americans have been threatening
India for the past few years not to
purchase the s-400 anti-missile system
from the Russians else we may think of
imposing catsar sanctions on India
right but India has gone ahead and
purchased the S 400 missile defense
system so now in the light of the
invasion of Ukraine it is a possibility
now that the Americans may go ahead and
impose these cats are sanctions or India
it won't be the first time America has
imposed sanctions on India
America imposed sanctions on India
in the aftermath of the 1998 nuclear
weapons tests
so it is possible now that the Americans
may decide to impose these katsa
sanctions on India which would be
an unfriendly and hostile action
in which case the entire quad becomes
untenable because
India and the US are the two most
powerful members of the Quad whose other
two members are Japan and Australia
if America imposes sanctions on India
can they continue to expect cooperation
from India in the indo-pacific against
China
so so the Americans may think of doing
this they are already thinking of doing
this I'm sure if they do it
they should consider all the
possibilities of what could happen after
that all the repercussions
do they want to do it do they not need
India in the
forthcoming struggle against China
the indo-pacific is the key to the to
America's future
Europe May soon be a lost case the
indo-pacific is the key to the future of
the world of the global order
and the Americans will lead India
support in that
so they need to think very carefully
whether they want to impose sanctions on
India which is a hostile action
let's see how it goes but yeah it is a
possibility that they may do that
ah World War III
so the question is will America or NATO
deploy their troops or give air support
to Taiwan and Taiwan also reported nine
Chinese fighter jets in the zone is
world war three coming
and harshal says looking at Russia
acquiring Ukraine so easily isn't it
going to motivate big countries like
China to acquire neighboring inferior
countries because America now looks like
a spectator's spectator will this ignite
World War III
are we witnessing
something that may lead
to the Third World War
okay so here's how it goes
history teaches us
that when you have
that when an existing hegemonic
superpower is threatened by a new Rising
power
in a geographical sphere of its
influence then war is inevitable
so when you have an established
superpower which is threatened by a new
Rising power let's say China
then once that new Rising power Rises
Beyond a certain point and when they
establish power declines Beyond a
certain point war is inevitable
so this would this is called the
thucydidist Trap I have spoken about
this before the Greek historian
tucsonite is
remarked about this during the course of
the Peloponnesian War which happened two
and a half thousand years before today
so the Americans and the Chinese may be
hurtling towards athusi Daddy's trap
scenario you will not see the beginning
of the third world war in Europe
but you may see the beginning of the
third world war happening in the
indo-pacific most likely in Taiwan if
the Chinese make a move in Taiwan the
Americans will have to intervene
militarily
and once the firing and the shooting
starts anything is possible so if the
third world war would happen it will
happen in the in the indo-pacific most
likely in the Taiwan region
and that could lead to the third world
war so most see the thing is nobody
wants a war the Chinese have a lot to
lose they will lose all the economic
progress they have they have built up
over the decades the Americans will lose
whatever they have nobody wants a war
but once you take the first step of
firing the first bullet anything can
happen so the place where from which the
third world war could erupt is the
indo-pacific the Taiwan region so it is
a possibility I would not say the
probability is zero there is a small
probability that it could happen in the
indo-pacific region in Taiwan maybe in
this decade it could happen who knows
let's see I hope it doesn't happen
war is terrible War
when you are watching war on YouTube or
TV it looks like something is it looks
like watching a movie
but it's it's not fun it's a terrible
thing it's it's tragic it causes the
loss of lives and all what is bad but
the history of the human species is a
history of War unfortunately
so yes a third world war could happen I
hope it doesn't happen but if like I
said earlier if somebody messes up
it may happen in the indo-pacific region
Amman says
admiration for authoritarian leaders is
condemnable though
this
hurts my feelings I'm very hurt
when did I express
admiration
for
Justin Trudeau
when did I do that
I do not have an admiration for Justin
Trudeau
so this really hurts my feelings I'm no
longer going to play this game I'm going
home
okay with that joke we come to the end
of today's session I hope I have given
you all some clarity on what's Happening
and what could happen in the future
making predictions is a Fool's errand I
have made some predictions
let's see how it goes so in short India
is doing the right thing in not getting
involved officially technically in this
matter India is staying neutral
technically but India is pursuing its
National interest understand this this
is not non-alignment India is strongly
and vigorously pursuing its National
interest and you can see this from the
way the Americans are so displeased and
ranting on Twitter
so it's essentially a move in favor of
Russia what India has done so that's
where we are today the Chinese could
start making moves on Indian Territory
in small ways in the coming days weeks
months yes you could see that and
possibly a big war May erupt in Asia in
the indo-pacific region in Taiwan if the
Chinese miscalculate and make their move
too early
but what we are witnessing now in real
time is the slow decline of the West in
the slow rise of the East who's going to
win we don't know but 20 years from from
today the Americans are going to be
significantly weaker than what they are
today that is a prediction I'm making
with certainty all right my friends
thank you everybody for your wonderful
questions I really appreciate it do I
have some questions in the live stream
I'm sure I have lots and lots and lots
but
I hope I have covered everything today
so thank you everybody thank you for
your questions and I will see you
tomorrow in tomorrow's live stream until
then take care
thank you for your support thank you for
your viewership
really appreciate it
I'll see you tomorrow bye